Guide to the Dean Johnson Papers 1982-2007 MSS 335
Fales Library and Special Collections
Dean Johnson Papers
1982 - 2007
MSS 335
Fales Library and Special Collections
3.0 boxes
The Dean Johnson Papers consists of materials documenting Dean Johnson's career as a party and club promotor and perfomer in New York City's Downtown club scene. Spanning over two decades, this collection contains promotional materials for parties organized by Johnson, as well as print and media coverage of Johnson's two bands, Dean and the Weenies and the Velvet Mafia.
Johnson, Dean
Arrangement
Materials have been arranged in series according to material formats. When dated, materials are arranged chronologically within series.
The collection is organized into the following five series:
SERIES I: Promotion
SERIES II: Sound recordings
SERIES III: Video recordings
SERIES IV: Data Storage
OVERSIZE- SERIES I: Posters
Biographical Note
Dean Johnson (1961–2007) moved to New York City in 1979 to study film at New York University, and quickly became an iconic figure in the New York City Downtown club scene. Johnson, at six foot six inches tall with a shaved head, was known for wearing tight dresses, huge sunglasses, and drop earrings. Working as a party and club promoter beginning in the 1980s, Johnson played an influential role in the emergence of the gay rock and roll subculture in New York City. He organized parties such as the Rock and Roll Fag Bar, Pubic Hair Club for Men, and HomoCorps, a gay themed night at CBGB. Johnson fronted two bands, Dean and the Weenies and the Velvet Mafia, playing the downtown club circuit and events such as Wigstock. He was also featured in two films depicting the underground New York Scene, “Mondo New York” and “Freaks, Glam Gods and Rock Stars.” Johnson was open about his work in the sex industry, and lived H.I.V. positive for two decades. In later years, Johnson explored blogging and writing, and hosted various readings where he and other writers presented their work. In 2007, Johnson died of an apparent drug overdose in Washington, DC, at the age of 46.
Sources:
Buckley, Cara. “Disquieting Death Stills the Night Life.” The New York Times, October 14, 2007.
Schindler, Paul. “Dean Johnson, 45, gay party promoter on Downtown scene.” The Villager, October 10 - 16, 2007.
Moynihan, Colin. “A Fond and Boisterous Memorial Is Held for a Symbol of Gay Night Life.” The New York Times, October 5, 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers. Audiovisual materials and computer disks have not been preserved and are not available to reseachers. Appointments are necessary for the use of manuscript and archival collections.
Provenance
The Dean Johnson Papers were donated to the Fales Library in 2012 by Johnson's sister, Beth Johnson.
Scope and Content
The Dean Johnson Papers consist of printed ephemera and media materials. Printed materials include magazines, periodicals, and posters of band performances and parties promoted by Johnson. Media includes audio and video recordings of performances, digital photos and data storage. Dated materials span the years from 1982- 2007.
Johnson, Dean; CD-Rs.; Digital art.; DVDs.; East Village (New York, N.Y.); Magazines (periodicals); New wave music.; Nightclubs.; Performance artists.; Posters.; Promotional materials.; Punk culture |z New York (State) |z New York.
- Series I: Promotion
  - HX Magazine: Issue 506, May 18th, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - HX Magazine: Issue 641, December 19th, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - HX Magazine: Issue 691, December 3, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - New York: Vol. 35, No. 32, September 23, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Next Magazine: Vol. 5, Issue 45, May 22, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Next Magazine: Vol. 8, Issue 16, October 27, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Next Magazine: Vol. 13, Issue 19, November 11, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Next Magazine: Vol. 14, Issue 43, April 27, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Press about Dean Johnson, March 25, 2005; undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Promotion Cards, 1990-1993; undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "This is Offensive" Decal, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series II: Sound recordings
  Conditions Governing Access
  These items have not been preserved, and are not currently available to researchers.
  - Dean and the Weenies: Live at the World, 1986 (Box 2, Media ID: 335.0005)
    Currently unavailable until duplication occurs.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements Note
    Original format: CD-R
  - Fuck You, 1988; Commercial Release (Box 2, Media ID: 335.0001)
    Original format: CD
  - We Know Where You Live- The Velvet Mafia, 1996; Commercial Release (Box 2, Media ID: 335.0002)
  - We Know Where You Live- The Velvet Mafia, 1998; Commercial Release (Box 2, Media ID: 335.0003)
  - Cheap But Not Free- The Velvet Mafia, 2004; Commercial Release (Box 2, Media ID: 335.0004)
  - Sibilance Issue #2, Track #8 Dean Johnson Talks About Buying A Girdle, undated (Box 2, Media ID: 335.0006)
- Series III: Video recordings
  - Downtown, 1982 (Box 2, Media ID: 335.0007)
    Original format: DVD-R
  - Dean and the Weenies: Limelight, November 17, 1985 (Box 2, Media ID: 335.002)
    [Unreadable Disc]
  - Dean and the Weenies: Pyramid; The World, May 21, 1988; May 6, 1986 (Box 2, Media ID: 335.0008)
  - Dean and the Weenies: Video Bar, Dallas Texas (1), 1989 (Box 2, Media ID: 335.0009)
  - Dean and the Weenies: Video Bar Dallas, Texas (2), Fuck You, 1989 (Box 2, Media ID: 335.001)
  - Dean and the Weenies: Video Bar, Dallas, Texas (3), You're No Good / You Boys, 1989 (Box 2, Media ID: 335.0011)
  - Clips of Dean Johnson in Lola Rocknrolla's Movies, Dragzilla 2002, TLTS and Blood 2004, Night of the Living Gay 2007, 2002, 2004, 2007 (Box 2, Media ID: 335.0012)
  - Velvet Mafia: CBGB, June 26, 2006 (Box 2, Media ID: 335.0013)
  - Velvet Mafia Sound Check: Webster Hall, May 2006 (Box 2, Media ID: 335.0014)
  - Dean Johnson Law Life, His Last Performance, September 18, 2007 (Box 2, Media ID: 335.0015)
  - Tribute to Dean Johnson a few days after his death: Rapture Cafe and Books NYC, October 10, 2007 (Box 2, Media ID: 335.0016)
  - Dean Johnson in the Lisa Jackson Documentary, 2007 (Box 2, Media ID: 335.0017)
  - Johnson Dean Dowg Reading for Filth, 2007 (Box 2, Media ID: 335.0018)
  - "Various videos that I put together and played in the background at Dean's memorial concert on at Don Hill's", May 30, 2008 (Box 2, Media ID: 335.0019)
  - A Couple of Velvet Mafia Videos and 1 Weenies, undated (Box 2, Media ID: 335.0023)
  - A Video Tribute to Dean Johnson by Robert O'Hare, undated (Box 2, Media ID: 335.0024)
  - Dean Johnson in "Freaks Glam God and Rockstars: The NYC Story", undated (Box 2, Media ID: 335.0021)
  - Dean Johnson and Velvet Mafia: Homocorps CBGB, undated (Box 2, Media ID: 335.0022)
  - Dean on Andy Warhol's "15 Minutes of Fame (Pilot Episode)", undated (Box 2, Media ID: 335.002)
- Series IV: Data Storage
  Data disks have not been preserved and are not available to reseachers.
  - Photos of Press Material, undated (Box 2, Media ID: 335.3.0001)
    Format: CD-R
  - Dean Johnson: Blogs, Fliers, Posters, Pictures, Press, and Some Lyrics, undated (Box 2, Media ID: 335.3.0002)
    [Blank disc]
- OVERSIZE- Series I: Posters
  - Critics Agree: Homocorps Rock Gay Scene!, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Dean Johnson Presents: Reading for Filth: "Queer Writers Read About Queer Sex", undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Dean Johnson and Daniel Nardico Present: Triple XXX The Dirtiest Part in NYC, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Dean Johnson's Homocorps Music Showcase, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Homocorps Present: Grrrl's Nite "Out'!, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - The Velvet Mafia, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - The Velvet Mafia, live at Area Code 10018, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)